拯救大兵瑞恩
爸?
Dad?
1944年6月6日
奥马哈海滩  绿D区
别挡住跳板  三十秒后登陆 愿主保佑你
Clear the ramp! 30 seconds! May God be with you!
左舷右舷听着  尽快攻占炮台
Port side and starboard side stick!Move fast and clear those mortar holes!
大家尽量分散
I want to see plenty of beach between men.
五个人就容易成为目标 一个人则能躲开
Five men is a juicy opportunity. One man is a waste of ammo.
别让沙子堵塞枪口  小心行事
Keep the sand out of your weapons! Keep those actions clear!
在滩头上见
I'll see you on the beach!
避开弹坑  分成左右两列
Clear the mortar hole! Right and left!
到旁边去
Over the side!
从左右方下水
Port and starboard!
谢谢
Thank yo...
长官  怎么办?
What now, sir?
长官  现在怎么办?
I said, 'What the hell do we do now, sir?"
米勒上尉...
Captain Miller! Captain Miller!
米勒上尉!霍瓦特中士!
Captain Miller! Sergeant Horvath!
叫你的弟兄攻上滩头  快
Move your men off the beach! Now!
大家听我命令  跟着我冲
Okay, you guys, get on my ass! Follow me!
长官  集合点在哪里? 总之不是这里
-Sir! What's the rallying point?  -Anywhere but here!
怎么办  长官? 快攻上海堤
-What now, sir?  -The seawall, move up to the seawall!
我要留下来!先攻占滩头再说
-Sir, I'm staying!   -Clear the beach to make way.
走出去就死定了
This is all we've got between us and the Almighty.
这滩头的每一处都被瞄准了
Every inch of this beach has been pre-sighted.
留下来必死无疑
You stay here, you're dead men!
妈妈...
Mama, Mama!
伏下来
Stay down, stay down!
你们是什么部队?104师的医疗营
-What are you guys?   -104th Medical Battalion,sir.
我们是来设立医疗站的 丢掉这废物
-We're here to set up field operations.  -Get rid of that crap!
拿起武器跟我来
Grab yourselves some weapons and follow me.
我中弹了!布格斯
-I'm hit!  -Briggs!
医护兵
Medic!
天啊  我中弹了!医护兵
-I'm hit low! God!  -Medic!
我们是海军抢滩大队
Navy Beach Battalion, sir!
我得清除这些障碍  为坦克开路
I've got to clear these obstacles. Make holes for the tanks!
装甲车都掉到海里了 长官  这是命令
-All the armour is floundering at sea.  -Orders, sir!
到别处去  这里交给我
Go somewhere else! I'm clearing this one.
来吧  布格斯
Come on, Briggs!
医护兵
Medic!
快走  快
Move, move!
来吧  快
Come on, move!
快走
Move, move!
海岸后勤工作队 装甲车都无法登岸
Shore party! No armour has made it ashore.
滩头上都没有DD坦克 D1缺口还没打开
We've got no DD tanks on the beach.Dog One is not open!
这里是谁指挥?
Who's in command here?
长官  是你
You are, sir!
霍瓦特中士? 你认得这是哪里吗?
Sergeant Horvath? Do you recognize where we are?
是原定的集合点 但却没有支援部队
Where we're supposed to be, but no one else is.
大家都走散了
Nobody's where they're supposed to be!
海岸后勤工作队
Shore party!
第一波攻击无效 无法攻占海滩
First wave ineffective! We do not hold the beach.
重复  无法攻占海滩
Say again, we do not hold the beach!
我们都混在一起了 这里有F、A和G连的弟兄
We're mixed up! We've got people from Fox,Able and George companies.
和海军爆破队员及陆战队长
Plus, we got some Navy demo guys and a beachmaster.
海岸后勤工作队...
Shore party, Shore party!
指挥官...
CAT-F, CAT-F, CA...
莱宾报到 有看到别人吗?
-Reiben here.  -Seen anybody else?
只有杰克森 梅利西报到
-Jackson,but that's it.  -Mellish here!
卡帕佐 德佛里斯特和韦德在后面
Caparzo! We've got DeForest back there with Wade!
他严重失血  韦德说他没救了
D.'s hurt so bad he's sprung a hundred leaks! Wade says he's used up!
去救其他人吧 我们走吧  他是军医
-Move on to somebody you can help.  -Let go, he's a battalion surgeon!
去叫他!韦德
-Get his attention!   -Wade!
韦德!韦德
Wade! Wade!
韦德  别这么做  太危险了
Wade, don't do it! It's too risky, too risky, Doc!
快滚回来
Get your ass back here!
把他带回来
Get him off the beach.
我办到了  我们替他止住血了
I've got it! We've stopped the bleeding!
去你的
Fuck!
混蛋  赶尽杀绝
Just give us a fucking chance, you son of a bitch!
韦德  走吧 你这个混蛋
Wade, come on! You son of a fucking cocksucker!
韦德  是梅利西  韦德
Wade, it's Mellish. Wade!
走吧  找到米勒了  走吧
Let's move! We found Miller! Let's move!
去你的
Fuck it!
伏下...
Get down, get down!
就只有你们几个吗?
This is all? This is all that's made it?
我们被分散了  一定还有人的
We got scattered pretty bad. There's bound to be more of us.
这样不够
It's not enough.
D1缺口是在右边还是左边?
Dog One exit. It's the cut to the right, or was it left?
不  维尔维里在左边 这里才是D1缺口
No. Vierville is to the left. This is Dog One.
他们在痛宰我们 根本没有机会战斗  不公平
They're killing us and we don't have a fucking chance! That ain't fair!
收集武器弹药 收集武器弹药
-Gather weapons and ammo!  -Gather weapons and ammo!
莱宾?你的手枪呢?
Reiben! Where's your BAR?
在水底 差点给敌军害我被淹死
Bottom of the Channel. The bitch tried to drown me.
再去找一支
Find a replacement.
拿爆破筒出来
Bangalores! Bring out some bangalores!
工兵来了 给我手榴弹
Engineers coming! Grenades, give me grenades!
把爆破筒运到前面去
Bangalores up the line! Bangalores up the line!
小心  爆破筒来了  来吧
Heads up! Bangers coming your way! Come on, come on!
杰克森报到 莱宾回来了
-Jackson here, sir!  -Reiben back, sir.
天啊
Oh, my God!
迫击炮来了
Mortars incoming!
再给我一支
One more, give me one more!
天啊  痛死我了  我快要死了
Oh, my God, it hurts! I'm going to die!
天啊...
Oh, my God! Jesus! Oh, my God!
放进去  继续
Come on, put it in. Keep it moving.
行了
We've got it.
天啊  你运气真好
Jesus! Lucky bastard.
快点
Move it! Keep it moving!
你不会死的  别看
You're not going to die. You're fine. Just don't look at it. Don't look at it!
用爆破筒来攻击  让开
Bangalores! Clear the shingle!
准备爆破  准备爆破
Fire in the hole! Fire in the hole!
准备爆破
Fire in the hole!
可以反攻了  找掩护 到沙坑的另一边
We're in business! Defilade! Other side of the hole!
给他吗啡
Give him some morphine.
行了  走吧
That's it, let's go.
检验过了  注射吗啡
Inspected, morphine.
一般处理
Routine.
优先处理
Priority.
他死了
He is gone
混蛋  过去
Son of a bitch! Get in there.
可恶  我动不了 梅利西  刺刀给我
-Fuck,I can't move!   -Mellish,give me your bayonet.
中士
Sarge.
两挺MG-42机枪  两支迫击炮 在前方二十码  左边三十码
Two MG-42s, two mortars. Add 20, left 30.
那有掩护物  若装甲车登陆后 会是最好的发射位置
There's defilade, but it's a good firing position if we can land the armour.
我们得打开这个缺口
We've got to get this draw open!
莱宾、梅利西  上吧 找到掩护就猛烈开火
-Reiben, Mellish! Let's get in the war!  -Take cover and put fire on that crew.
戴维斯、德伯纳多 杨、瓦克!快准备
Davis, DeBernardo, Young, Valk! Get ready!
开火
Covering fire!
去吧
Go, go, go!
敌军的炮火很厉害
It's a goddam firing squad.
要逃出这里  只有这样
It's the only way we can get everybody out of here.
肖特、佩森、麦唐纳、帕克斯 你们是下一组!
Short, Payton, McDonald, Parkes! You're next!
何不干脆给我们眼罩 不就行了吗?
Why not just hand out blindfolds, Captain?
唯有出去拼命  开火
All we can do here is die! Covering fire!
快...
Go, go, go!
快点... 去你的
Come on, come on, come on! Go, God damm it!
杰克森 是
-Jackson.  -Sir.
看见那弹坑吗? 在那里应能躲开机枪的攻击
See that impact crater? should give you defilade from the machine gun position.
躲进去好好表现枪法 等我的命令
Get in there and give me some fire discipline. Wait for my command.
去吧
Go!
若你妈看见你这样 会很担忧的
If your mother saw you do that, she'd be very upset.
我还以为你就是我妈呢
I thought you were my mother.
别远离我  天主
Be not Thou far from me, O Lord.
主啊  很抱歉我曾经激怒你
Oh, my God. I am heartily sorry for having offended Thee.
我对此深感懊悔 请听我的祷告
I detest my sins for having offended Thee, O Lord. Listen to me, Lord.
赐我力量  助我抗敌
All my strength! Haste Thee to help me.
D1缺口打开了  往这边走
Dog One exit, right here!
大家反攻
We're in business!
快
Move, move!
莱宾 去吧  中士
Reiben. Go, Sarge!
莱宾
Reiben!
来吧  多里
Come on, Doyle!
中士
Sarge!
多里  打开喷火器
Flame! Doyle, do it!
别开枪  让他们吃吃苦头
Don't shoot! Let them burn!
右边
On the right!
你们一起死吧  混蛋
I'll give you "comrade", you son of a bitch!
小心  转过去
Look out! Turn around, turn around.
去干掉他们
Flush them out!
停火...住手...
Cease fire, cease fire! Cut it out, cut it out!
停火!
Cease fire!
这是SC第3队  重复 D1缺口已经打开了
Sugar Cane, Sugar Charlie Three. Say again, Dog One is open.
派出推土机 我在这里等待配合侧翼
Send in the dozers. I'm waiting here to tie in my flanks.
什么?
What?
什么? 抱歉  我听不懂你在说什么
What? I'm sorry, I can't understand what you're saying!
他说什么?
What did he say, what did he say?
我洗过手准备吃饭了
Look, I washed for supper!
谁有火箭筒?真该死
Who's got a bazooka,Goddammit
笨蛋  你看 是希特勒青年团小刀
Hey, Fish. Look at this, a Hitler Youth knife.
现在是犹太面包刀了  对吧?
And now it's a Shabbat challah cutter, right?
别停下来
Keep it moving!
意大利、法国、非洲
好惨烈的景象
That's quite a view.
没错
Yes, it is.
很惨烈
Quite a view.
瑞恩
“亲爱的博伊德先生 你应该已经得悉...”
"Dear Mr Brian Boyd. No doubt by now you have received full information"-
“你儿子的死讯”
"about the untimely death of your son."
“说什么也无法 减轻您的哀痛”
"No words can ever relieve your grief."
“本部队对他的死深感惋惜 他是个优秀的士兵”
"Our outfiit has felt his loss greatly..." "He was a fiine soldier"-
“并深信我们所从事的...”
"and believed strongly in what we were doing..."
“我们参与了大战中 最重要的军事行动”
"We were involved in one of the most important operations of the war."
“艾尔使我们能团结一致”
"Al was the one who held us all together."
“他身先士卒”
"He was the first to volunteer."
“那里有四千人的部队开过”
"We passed a road where over 4,000 troops had passed."
“尊夫尽忠职守...”
"Your husband served in a unit whose duty is to place itself beyond..."
“大家都很怀念他”
"...which we all cherish and hold dear..."
“李等人的死 对军团打击甚大”
"The loss of Lee and others like him is a distinct blow to the regiment."
“我们了解你想知道...”
"We understand your desire to learn about"-
“他去世时的情形”
"the circumstances leading to his death."
上校  有件事想告诉你
Colonel, I've got something you should know about.
这两人在诺曼第阵亡
These two men died in Normandy.
这位死于奥哈马海滩 肖恩瑞恩
-This one at Omaha Beach.  -"Sean Ryan."
这位死于犹他 彼得瑞恩
-This man at Utah.  -"Peter Ryan."
这位上周在新几内亚阵亡
This man was killed last week in New Guinea.
丹尼尔瑞恩
"Daniel Ryan."
他们是兄弟
The three men're brothers,sir.
他们的妈妈会在下午 接到这三封电报
I just learned that this afternoon their mother's going to get all three telegrams.
在抢滩前一晚 他们的四弟跟随101空降师
There's also a fourth brother who parachuted in with 101st Airborne -
在诺曼第某处跳伞
the night before the invasion. He is somewhere in Normandy.
他还活着吗? 不知道
-Is he alive?   -We don't know.
跟我来
Come with me.
该死
Goddammit.
四兄弟都在第29师的 同一个连队服役
All four were in the same company in the 29th Division -
但苏利文兄弟在朱诺送命后 我们便分开了他们
but we split them up after the Sullivan brothers died on the Juneau.
能联络上四弟詹姆斯吗?
Any contact with the fourth son, James?
不能  他空降在距纽维15哩的 内陆  深入了敌区
No. He was dropped 15 miles inland near Neuville, behind German lines.
根本无法知道他空降在哪里
Mac, there is no way you can know where he was dropped.
据报101空降师的人失散了
First report from lke's people at SHAEF said the 101st is scattered.
诺曼第有很多 被空投错误的部队
There are misdrops all over Normandy.
就算瑞恩能安然降落 也无法找到他
Assuming Private Ryan even survived the jump, he could be anywhere.
可能他早已阵亡
In fact, he's probably K.I.A.
老实说  若我们派出搜救部队
And frankly, if we go sending some sort of rescue mission, -
他们就得穿越德军固守区
flat-hatting throughout German reinforcements along our advance, -
那一定也会阵亡的
they're going to be K.I.A., too.
这里有封信
I have a letter here...
是很久以前给波士顿的 比克斯比太太的信  听我读
...written a long time ago to a Mrs Bixby in Boston. So bear with me.
“女士”
"Dear Madam."
“我已从麻萨诸塞州 上将副官的...”
"I have been shown in the files of the War Department a statement" -
“战争部档案得悉”
"of the Adjutant General of Massachusetts" -
“你是五位在沙场上”
'that you are the mother of five..."
“光荣阵亡的战士的母亲”
"...sons who have died gloriously on the field of battle."
“我感到我的言辞薄弱无力”
"I feel how weak and fruitless must be any words of mine" -
“根本无法安抚你的悲伤”
'that would attempt to beguile you from the grief' -
“也无法弥补你的损失”
"of a loss so overwhelming..."
“但我必须要在此向你致谢”
"...but I can't refrain from tendering the consolation that may be found" -
“他们是为了拯救国家而死”
"in the thanks of the republic they died to save."
“愿天主安抚你的丧子之痛”
"May our Heavenly Father assuage the anguish of your bereavement" -
“让你永远怀念远去的挚爱”
"and leave you only the cherished memory of the loved and lost" -
“神圣的荣耀都归于你们”
"and the solemn pride that must be yours to have laid such a sacrifice" -
“因你们为自由 付出了重大的代价”
"upon the altar of freedom. Yours very sincerely and respectfully," -
“林肯敬上”
"Abraham Lincoln."
那孩子还活着 我们要派人去找他
That boy is alive. We are going to send somebody to find him.
然后带他远离战场
And we are going to get him the hell out of there.
奥哈马海滩 登陆后第三天
后勤官在海滩 寻找被炸毁的碉堡
The Quartermaster's up the beach a way. Look for a blown-up bunker.
我是C连的米勒 上尉  请进
-Miller,Charlie Company.  -Go on in,Captain.
若六点以前无法下坦克的话
If we don't off-load the Shermans by 0600 -
一整师的部队 就会被困在卡伦坦
we'll have a division stuck at Carentan with its pants around its ankles.
再说明一下
Well, you let me know of it.
让C连死守维尔维里 直到装甲兵开到
Let Charlie Company hold at Vierville 'til we can get the armour there.
传令兵
Runner!
原本空降师该打开缺口的 但他们却投错地方
Airborne was supposed to win an open door for us, but misdropped, -
全都失散了  你的情况如何?
and scattered all their sticks into the wind. What's your situation?
第四区攻下了
Yes, sir... Sector Four is secure.
我们摧毁了这几处的 88公厘炮
We took out towed 88s here, here and here.
敌军有四部坦克和一些运兵车
They got four Shermans and some deuce-and-a-halves.
这两处的布雷区很大
These two minefields are actually one big one.
我们到了中心地带 发现地雷的密度很高
We went up the middle of it, but it turned into a mixed high-density field.
什么地雷都有  S44型、S42型
A little bit of everything; Sprengmine 44s, Schumne 42s, -
散片型地雷、A-200 连侦测器都无法找到
pot mines, A-200s, the little wooden bastard the detectors don't pick up.
这里埋了T43型大地雷 大概想炸我们的坦克
Here, they placed big mushrooms, Teller mine 43s, I guess for our tanks, -
从这里到村庄的边缘
from here right up to the edge of the village, right here.
已记下位置  通知了工兵
We marked them and called the engineers.
有遇上反抗吗? 没想像的那么强
-Resistance?  -We had higher support expectations.
有一连没配大炮的346步兵
There was a company without artillery. Wehrmacht. 346th Infantry.
由卡夫加帕指挥 我们俘虏了23人
Von Lucke Kampfgruppe. We ended up with 23 prisoners.
已交由29师的宪兵处置
We turned them over to MPs from the 29th.
我军的伤亡呢?
What about our casualties?
伤亡人数是...35死  70人伤
Well, the figure is... We're 35 dead, times two wounded.
他们就是不肯放弃那些重炮
They just didn't want to give up those 88s.
任务很艰巨  所以才找你
It was a tough assignment. That was why you got it.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
约翰
John...
你又有一项任务了 是  长官
-I've got another one for you.   -Yes, sir.
是上级直接交办的
It's straight from the top.
我希望你和我带一队人 到纽维去执行公关任务
I wish. You and I are taking a squad to Neuville on a PR mission.
由你带队吗?
Oh, are you leading a squad?
一位二等兵死了三兄弟 所以能回家
A private in the 101st lost three brothers and he's got a ticket home.
为何要去纽维呢? 他们觉得他在那里
-Why Neuville?  -They think he's there.
他是被错投的空降部队之一
Part of all those Airborne misdrops.
现在兵荒马乱 要找一名士兵很难
It won't be easy finding one soldier in the middle of this goddam war.
就像大海捞针般
Like finding a needle in a stack of needles.
那连上兄弟怎么办?
What about the company?
最好的跟我们 其他的加入B连
We take the pick of the litter, the rest goes to Baker.
天啊  他们夺走了你的连?
Jesus Christ! They took away your company?
部队是军方的  我们唯有遵命
It wasn't mine, it was the Army's. So they told me, anyway.
给我莱宾、杰克森、韦德 贝斯里和卡帕佐
Get me Reiben on BAR, Jackson, Wade, Beasley and Caparzo.
贝斯里死了 那找梅利西
-Beasley's dead.  -Alright,Mellish then.
有人会法语吗? 据我所知没有
-Do have a guy who speaks French?    -Not that I know of.
塔尔博特呢? 今早死了
What about Talbot? This morning.
我要去找个翻译员
I'm going to try and dig up another interpreter.
到滩头的车辆调度场集合
Assemble at the battalion motor pool on the beach.
该怎么办? 听着  什么?
What are we going to do? Listen up. What?
我要用大块乳酪塞进你的屁股 好让你棺材盖国旗回家
Go home wrapped in the American flag with a hunk of cheese in your ass.
我以为你喜欢塞屁股的 什么?
I thought you liked it in the ass. What?
立正
Attention!
稍息  我要找提摩西厄本下士
As you were. I'm looking for Corporal Timothy Upham.
是  我就是厄本
Yes, I'm Upham.
你会说法语和德语? 是  长官
-Do you speak French and German?    -Yes, sir.
有没有口音? 法语有
-How's your accent?   -Slight one in French.
但德语很纯正 很好
-My German's clean.    -Very good.
你已被派给我了 收拾行囊  我们要到纽维去
You've been re-assigned to me. Grab your gear, we're going to Neuville.
这是何时更新的? 早上八点半
-When was this updated?    -As of 8:30 this morning.
这是12SS坦克部队 还有两队人向南推进
This is the 12th SS Panzer. These are the two axes advancing south.
纽维有德军 我知道  下士
There are Germans in Neuville. I understand, Corporal.
纽维有很多德军 有问题吗?
There are a lot of Germans in Neuville. You've got a problem with that?
我没作战过 只懂绘制地图和翻译
Please consider that I've never been in combat. I make maps and translate.
我需要会法语和德语的人
I need someone who speaks French and German.
原来的两位阵亡了 我从新兵训练后就没拿过枪
My two guys were killed. I haven't held a weapon since training.
基本训练时开过枪吧?
Did you fire the weapon in Basic training?
开过  长官 那去准备一下
-Yes, sir.   -Well, then get your gear.
长官  我能带...
Sir, may I bring...
能带打字机吗?
May I bring my typewriter, sir?
是  长官
Yes, sir.
谢谢你
Thank you very much.
那是纪念品吗? 不是
-Is that a souvenir?    -No, sir.
慢慢来
Take your time.
下士  凡事都有好的一面
You should look on the bright side of things, Corporal.
是 还有  这个也没有用
-Yes. -For one thing, you don't need those.
但你需要这个 对  要这个
-You'll need that.   -Yes. I'll need this, not that.
你好 干嘛?
Hey! Hey!
你是不是想找死?
You want your head blown off?
别再用你的爪子碰我 回去你的岗位
Don't touch me with those rat claws again. Get the fuck back in formation!
我只是想问你来自哪里
I was just wondering where you're from.
卡帕佐  对吧? 滚开  下士
-Caparzo,is it?  -Drop dead,Corporal.
知道了
Gotcha.
每次你向上尉敬礼 就会惹来德军袭击他
Every time you salute the Captain,you make him a target for the Germans.
对不起 帮帮忙  别那么做
-I'm sorry.  -Do us a favour.Don't do it.
尤其是 当我站在他旁边时  懂吗?
Especially when I'm standing next to him.Capisci?
懂了 下士  那是什么书?
-Capisco.  -Corporal,what's your book about?
当心你的枪 对不起
Watch your rifle. Sorry.
是关于行军时 发展手足之情的方法
It's about the brotherhood that develops between soldiers during war.
手足之情? 你懂什么是手足之情?
Brotherhood? What do you know about brotherhood?
要注意这砘
Get a load of this guy, Fish.
你何不去问上尉是哪里人呢?
Why don't you ask the Captain where he's from?
去问他  他什么都会告诉你的
Ask the Captain. He'll tell you everything you want to know about him.
解释给我听
Explain the maths of this to me.
八个人为何要 冒险救一个人呢?
Where is the sense in risking the lives of the eight of us to save one guy?
20度  有人想回答吗?
20 degrees. Anybody wants to answer that?
莱宾  想想那可怜虫的妈妈吧
Reiben, think about the poor bastard's mother.
医护兵  我也有妈妈
Hey, Doc, I've got a mother.
你有妈妈  中士也有妈妈
You've got a mother, Sarge has got a mother.
我敢说上尉也有妈妈
Shit, I bet even the Captain's got a mother.
也许上尉没有  但我们全都有
Maybe not the Captain, but the rest of us.
“不问原因  只求为国牺牲”
"Their's is not to reason why their's is but to do and die"
下士  那是什么鬼意思?
What the fuck is that supposed to mean, Corporal?
我们都该死吗?
We're all supposed to die?
厄本说的是我们的职责 是  长官
-Upham's talking about our duty.  -Yes, sir.
我们全都得服从命令
We all have orders to follow.
是的  长官  谢谢 就算任务是“苦差”?
Yes, sir. Thank you. Even if the mission is "FUBAR"?
这才更加要服从
Especially if the mission is "FUBAR".
“苦差”是什么? 是德语
-What's "FUBAR"?  -It's German.
没听过
Never heard of that...
长官  我对此有点意见
Sir, I have an opinion on this matter.
说出来听听吧
By all means, share it with the squad.
我的想法是
From my way of thinking, -
这次任务 浪费了宝贵的军事资源
this mission is a misallocation of valuable military resources.
是吗?继续
Yeah? Go on.
我觉得上帝赐给我打仗的天分
It seems to me that God gave me a sepcial gift made me a fine instrument of warfare.
莱宾  听好  这样抱怨才对 继续  杰克森
Reiben,pay attention.Now, this is the way to gripe.Continue,Jackson.
要是他派我这个狙击手
If He was to put me and this sniper rifle anywhere up to and including -
到希特勒一哩范围内
one mile of Adolf Hitler with a clear line of sight, sir...
大家就能收拾行囊回家 战争就结束了  阿们
Pack your bags, fellas, the war is over. Amen.
乡巴佬  这主意不错
That's brilliant, bumpkin.
上尉  你呢?你不会抱怨吗?
What about you, Captain? You don't gripe at all?
我是上尉  身负重任 不会向你抱怨
I don't gripe to you. I'm a captain. There's a chain of command.
上级永远是发牢骚的对象
Gripe always go up.
你向我发牢骚 我向我上级发牢骚  如此类推
You gripe to me, I gripe to my superior officers, and so on.
我不会在你面前发牢骚 你是突击队员  应该明白
I don't gripe in front of you. You should know that as a Ranger.
对不起  就当你不是上尉 或我是少校吧
I'm sorry, but let's say that you weren't a captain or that I was a major.
你会说什么?
What would you say?
那样我就会说 这项任务棒极了
In that case, I'd say, "This is an excellent mission" -
意义重大  值得我全力以赴
"with a valuable objective worthy of my best efforts."
而且我对瑞恩的母亲 感到深切的悲痛
"Moreover, I feel heartfelt sorrow for the mother of Private Ryan" -
为了慰藉她 我愿意赔上我与部下的性命
"and I'll lay down my life and those of my men, especially yours, Reiben," -
尤其是你  莱宾
'to ease her suffering."
他很棒 我喜欢他
He's good. I love him.
算了
Fine!
打雷! 闪电!
-Thunder!  -Flash!
厄本  到那边去 莱宾  你们四个过去
Upham, over there. Reiben, you four go.
去吧!
Go, go, go, go!
很高兴看见你 希尔中士  救星来了
You are a sight for sore eyes. Sergeant Hill, our reliefs showed up.
有多少人? 八个  但不是救兵
-How many are you?   -Eight. We're not your relief.
为什么? 我们来找二等兵瑞恩
What do you mean, sir? We're here for a Private Ryan.
谁? 瑞恩?为什么?
Who? Ryan? What for?
他在这里吗? 大概在镇的另一边
-Is he here?  -Maybe on the other side of the town.
周围都有德军  很难通过
It's hard to get to. The Germans punched a hole in our centre.
我军给德军切断 他叫什么名字?
-They cut us right in two.  -What's his name,again?
瑞恩  詹姆斯瑞恩 隶属101空降师
Ryan, James Ryan. He dropped in with the 101st.
高德曼  找传令兵来 传令兵
Goldman, get me a runner! Runner!
来吧
Come on!
琼斯  让开
Jonesy, make a hole up there!
我们为东面的炮火所阻
We got stopped by fire from the eastward.
德军聚集了两个团的兵力
The Germans have been reinforcing two regiments all day.
已经有四十五分钟没有动静
It's been quiet for 45 minutes.
德军正把火力集中于西面
The Germans concentrate their fire westward.
谁在广播? 达伍德迪撒多夫
Who's that on the loudspeaker? Dagwood Duesseldorf.
友善的政战官
Our friendly neighbourhood morale officer.
“自由神像完蛋了”
"The Statue of Liberty is kaput."
想扰乱我们军心
That's disconcerting.
笨蛋  你爹的包皮已给割掉了
Your father was circumcised by my rabbi, you prick!
躲好
Cover!
去吧
Go!
去你的臭混蛋 伏下
You sadistic fucking animals! Get down.
敌人知道我军通讯中断 所以针对传令兵
They know we're not in direct contact. They'll single out the runners.
为什么要射杀他们?
Why do they shoot them up?
不能留活口  以防军情外泄 我们也会这样做
As long as his lungs are working, he carries the message. We'd do the same.
不  我们不会 韦德  准备起程
No, we wouldn't! Wade! Get them ready to travel.
博伊德 来吧
Boyd! Come on!
再试一遍  设法通知 汉米尔上尉  我们正赶过去
Try again! Let Captain Hamill know we're coming.
纽维其他地方怎么样?
What's the rest of Neuville like?
接着会看到两层建筑物 有很多窗户
The next block's got two-storey buildings. A lot of windows.
有一广场可作藏身之用
There's a square with good cover.
带我去  中士  留在这里
Show me. Sarge, hold right here!
遵命
Yes, sir!
别在这里挨打  到里面躲避
Stay out of this enfilade and use the buildings.
到左边去  边走边开火 我们各派两人
Try a left hook. Shoot and scoot. Two of yours, two of mine.
黑斯亭斯、高德曼  到前面去
Hastings, Goldman! Up front!
莱宾、卡帕佐 通讯仍受敌军干扰
Reiben, Caparzo. They're still jamming us.
尽快到角落去  小心行事
Short runs, high and low at the corners. It's going to be tight.
准备进行近身战  去吧
Be prepared for close contact. Go.
厄本  跟霍瓦特中士待在一起
Upham! You stay with Sergeant Horvath.
上尉  我会像内裤般粘着他
Stay here! I'll wear him like underwear, Captain. You stay with me.
广场闸口在大楼的尽头
Past the end of the block are the gates of the square.
好 好的
Good. Alright.
莱宾  上尉从哪里来的?
Reiben, where's the Captain from?
猜中的话有奖 奖金三百块
If you figure it out, you'll get a prize. 300 bucks, last I heard.
大家下注  最少五块
The company's got a pool. Five bucks gets you in.
就在拐弯处  躲到闸门后面去
It's around this corner. Defilade right up to those gates.
一定有人知道他来自何方
Somebody must know where he's from.
我跟他一起那么久也毫无头绪
I've been with him since Casserene Pass. I don't have a clue.
我的足踝很痛 战事没结束已经要坐轮椅
My ankles are killing me. I'll need a wheelchair before the war is over.
老天  就跟老妇一样
That's it! Oh, my God! That ankle is like an old woman.
就像...老天
Like an old... Oh, God!
莱宾?你连他上哪所学校 也不知道?
Reiben. So you don't even know where he went to school?
他没念书 是军部用大兵尸体组装而成
He didn't go to school. They assembled him at OCS out of dead Gls.
我知道他的来历
Pay attention to detail. I know where he's from and what he did -
因为我看得仔细
because I pay attention to detail.
厄本  别信他的鬼话
Hey, Upham! Careful you don't step in the bullshit.
去吧 打雷
Do it. Thunder!
打雷  不然开火
Thunder, or we will fire on you!
梅利西、卡帕佐  过来
Mellish, Caparzo, come here!
叫他们表明身分
Tell them to show themselves.
问问德军在哪里
Ask them where the Germans are.
他说什么? 孩子
What is he saying? Something about the children.
孩子? 他想我们带走孩子
Kids? He wants us to take them.
不行  不能带走孩子
No, no. We can't take the kids.
不可以  不行
We can't take the kids! No, no!
他们以为这样较安全 跟着我们不会安全
They think they'll be safe. They won't be safe with us!
你疯了?听从上尉的命令
Are you nuts? Listen to the Captain!
他们以为孩子会安全一点
They think they'll be safe with us.
什么地方也不会安全 卡帕佐  交回孩子
It's not safe anywhere. Caparzo! Put that kid back!
卡帕佐  把孩子还给他们 请放心
Caparzo, put the girl back! It's OK, it's OK.
交回孩子
Give that kid back!
厄本  怎么说请放心? 他让我想起外甥女
Upham, how do you say, "It's OK?" I can't. She reminds me of my niece.
把孩子交回去
Get the kid back up there!
最少也该把她带到下个市镇
We should at least take her to the next town.
我们有任务在身 不是来救孩子
We're not here to do that, we're here to follow orders!
中士  把孩子接过来
Sarge, take this goddam kid!
躲好
Cover, cover!
糟糕
No!
可恶  哪里射过来的?
Goddammit! Where did that come from?
听到枪声前他已倒地
He was on the ground before we heard the shot.
是我就会到那里
That's where I'd be.
我看不到 450码外  也许在阴暗处
I didn't see it. 450 yards, maybe a shade under.
大家别冒险出去 那枪手很厉害
I wouldn't venture out there, fellas. This sniper's got talent!
别哭  我带你找爸妈
Please don't cry. I'll take you back to Mama and Papa. Please don't cry.
来吧
Come on.
卡帕佐
Carpy!
上尉 撑着  卡帕佐
Captain! Hold on, Caparzo.
扶我起来  我走得动
Help me up. I can walk.
卡帕佐  别动
Caparzo, stay still!
两格  风向偏左
Two clicks. Left wind.
笨蛋
Fish!
上尉?看到他吗?他怎么了?
Captain, can you see him? How is he?
韦德  别乱来
Wade, you stay put.
上尉  他哪里中枪?
Where is he shot, Captain?
看得到他吗? 别出去
Can you see him? You stay there!
可恶  躺下来
Damn it! Stay down!
你怎么了?你中了枪 要我照顾吗?
What's the matter with you? Am I going to take care of you if you get hit?
笨蛋  过来
Fish, come over here!
卡帕佐  躺下来别动
Carpy, put your head down! Why can't you put your head down?
天主  我信靠你
Oh, my God, I trust in Thee.
别让我蒙羞  别让敌人战胜我
Let me not be ashamed. Let not my enemies triumph over me.
抄下来  替我寄出去
Copy it. Copy it and send it for me.
放下来  你自己寄
You're going to send it yourself. Put it down!
信沾了血 我知道
-It's got blood on it!   -I see it.
给我爸的  沾了血  笨蛋
It's... It's to my dad. It's got blood on it, Fish.
打中了  伏下
We got him. Stay down.
伤得很重? 胸口中弹  或许肺给打中了
How bad is it? Chest, maybe lung shot.
把大炮放到街上
Get that.30 up the street!
报告情况 上面安全
Detail! Clear, up!
下面安全
Clear, down!
老早说过不能带孩子
That's why we can't take children.
霍瓦特中士  检查武器
Sergeant Horvath, do an ammo check.
厄本  把水壶装满
Upham, canteens. Fill them up.
希尔中士 是的  长官
-Sergeant Hill.   -Yes, sir.
召集弟兄  在广场西北角集合
Gather your men. We'll form up at the northwest corner of the square.
杰克森 是
-Jackson.   -Sir!
梅利西  去检查那座塔 尽快回来  快去吧
Mellish. Check the tower, hustle back here. Right now, go!
去他的瑞恩
Fuck Ryan!
打雷 闪电  进来吧
Thunder! Flash! Come on in!
我们在找汉米尔上尉
Hey, guys. We're looking for Captain Hamill.
那边  过了广场就到 过了广场
Down there, across the square. Across the square.
提防狙击手
Go easy. Watch for snipers.
请坐
Sit down.
吉米  叫汉米尔上尉过来
Jimmy T. Go and find Captain Hamill. Bring him here.
什么?上面吗? 我怎么知道?自己去找
-What? Up there?   -How should I know? Go and look!
谢谢你  智障
Thank you, you moron.
先在这里休息一下
Alright. You guys just flake out here for a while.
我要把石子倒出来
Let me get this goddam hitchhiker out of my boot.
放下武器 立刻放下
Put your weapons down! Drop them now!
我会开枪的
I'll shoot you!
放下武器
Drop, drop 'em!
立刻放下武器
Put 'em down!
上面安全了
Clear, up!
可恶
Shit, shit!
上面安全了
Clear, up!
下面也安全了
Clear, down!
这样子够让人变老了
Enough to make you old.
但愿如此
Let's hope so.
101师前导部队的汉米尔 第二突击队的米勒
Hamill, Pathfinders 101st. Miller, 2nd Rangers.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们在找二等兵瑞恩 他是你的属下
We're looking for a Private Ryan. He's part of your outfit.
有可能找到他吗?
Any chance that you policed him up?
路上的情况如何? 风光明媚  弹药快用光了
How was the road in? Scenic. We lost most of our ammo.
还死了一位队员
Not to mention one of our men.
中尉 把火箭筒调换到右边的路旁
Lieutenant! Redeploy that bazooka to the right side of the road.
去带瑞恩过来
And get Ryan up here!
瑞恩...到前面来
Ryan! Ryan! Front and centre! Ryan!
我们的大爷来了
Here comes our boy.
我早说他是个混蛋
I told you he was an asshole.
二等兵瑞恩报到 稍息
Private Ryan reporting as ordered. At ease.
第二突击队的米勒上尉 有话跟你说
Captain Miller, 2nd Rangers, wants a word with you.
这边
This way.
蹲下吧
Alright. Take a knee.
二等兵  有个坏消息要告诉你
Private, I'm afraid I have some bad news for you.
这真是让人难以启齿...
Well, there isn't any really easy way to say this, so...
我就直说吧  你的兄弟死了
...so I'll just say it. Your brothers are dead.
我们奉命来找你
We have orders to come and get you...
你可以回家了
...because you're going home.
老天  我兄弟死了
Oh, my God! My brothers are dead!
我本想带他们去钓鱼的
I was going to take them fishing when we got home.
对不起  詹姆斯 真是不知该说什么
I'm so sorry, James. I can't tell you how much.
他们是怎样死的? 阵亡
-How did they die?   -They were killed in action.
没有可能
That can't be.
他们才在念中学
They can't be my brothers. They're still in grammar school.
你是詹姆斯瑞恩? 对
-You're James Ryan?   -Yeah.
爱阿华州的 詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩?
James Francis Ryan from lowa?
明尼苏达州的 詹姆斯腓德利克瑞恩
James Frederick Ryan, Minnesota.
那表示我弟弟没事吗? 对  我确信他们很好
-Does that mean my brothers are OK?   -Yeah,I'm sure they're fine.
你确定? 我们找的不是这个瑞恩
Are you sure? We're looking for a different Ryan.
只是误会而已
It's just a big foul-up.
你怎么能确定? 怎么知道是不是又弄错了
How can you be sure? How do you know that the foul-up isn't -
原来是他的弟弟没事
that his brothers are OK, and...
中尉 麻烦你了
Lieutenant. I'm sorry for the trouble.
我在离开前才刚给他们写信 我得回家去了
I just wrote them a letter before I left. I've got to get home.
我要立刻回家  我想回家
I've got to get home right now. I want to go home.
我们的瑞恩在哪里呢? 不知道
Where is our Ryan? Don't know.
可以跟指挥官联络一下吗? 瑞恩隶属于什么单位?
Are you in touch with your CO? What unit's Ryan in?
506团的B连 那个断脚的砘锸506团的
Baker Company, 506th. The guy with the broken foot's in 506th.
我想是C连吧 你想?
-Charlie, I think.   -You think?
瑞恩?我不知道...老天
Ryan? Don't know... Man!
你们在哪里降落? 维尔维里
-Where was your dropzone?    -Vierville.
维尔维里?那怎会到这来的?
Vierville? How did you end up here?
问倒我了 C-47受到猛烈的攻击
You got me, sir. The C-47 took heavy fire.
机师拼命闪避炮火
Pilot went crazy turning every which way.
跳伞时炮火更猛 情况混乱  我就来了这里
We took more fire in the drop. It got messy. I ended up here.
我没见过我的队友 天晓得他们在哪里
I haven't seen a single guy from my stick. God knows where they are.
有B连的人谈到空降区在哪吗
Did anybody from Baker Company talk about where the dropzone was?
没有  但大家的集合点一样
No, but they had the same rallying point as us.
指出来
Show me.
我们累透了 再待三小时  入夜后出发
My men are beat. We'll hold up here for three hours and pull out after dark.
这镇上有三星级饭店什么的吗
Got anything left in this town, like a three-star hotel?
有干净的床单、枕头 和客房服务吗?
Something with clean sheets, soft pillows and room service?
舒适的教堂如何? 也好
-How about a nice, comfy church? -We'll take that.
有什么消息?战况如何?
What have you heard? How is it all falling together?
我们攻下了滩头堡 但蒙蒂却慢条斯理的进军康城
We got the beachhead secured,but Monty's taking his time moving on Caen.
要他准备好我们才能撤军 大家高估他了
-We can't pull out'til he's ready,so...  -That guy's overrated.
我同意 要拿下康城才能攻取圣罗
-No argument here.  -You take Caen to take Saint-L8.
要攻取瓦隆尼先要拿下圣罗 瓦隆尼之后是瑟堡
-You gotta take St-L8 to take Valognes. -Valognes,you've got Cherbourg.
瑟堡之后是巴黎 最后是柏林
-Cherbourg,you've got Paris.  -Paris,you've got Berlin.
然后就能回家
And then that big boat home.
你在这里能帮到我很多 但我了解你的任务
I could really use you around here, but I understand what you're doing.
是吗? 我也有几个兄弟
-You do?  -I've got a couple of brothers myself.
原来是这样 祝你好运
Oh. Good luck.
谢谢 不  我是说真的
-Thank you.   -No, I mean it.
找他出来  带他回家
Find him. Get him home.
你的手怎么了?
What's with your hand?
不知道
I don't know.
在朴次茅斯上船后就是这样
It started in Portsmouth when we went down for embarkation.
偶尔会这样 你该找别的工作
-It comes and goes.  -You have to find yourself a new job.
这工作不适合你了
This one doesn't seem to agree with you any more.
干嘛?
What?
干嘛? 没什么
-What?   -Nothing.
在安济奥那小子叫什么名字?
What was the name of that kid at Anzio?
用手倒立走路那个
The one who walked on his hands -
唱着空中飞人之歌那个?
and was singing that song about the man on the flying trapeze?
维驰奥 维驰奥
Vecchio. Vecchio!
不错  他是个笨蛋
Yeah, Vecchio. He was a goofy kid.
喜欢在别人的外套上尿出 一个“V”字  代表维驰奥
I remember he used to pee a "v" on everybody's jackets. For "vecchio".
代表胜利 维驰奥
For victory. Vecchio.
他长得很矮 是个侏儒吧?
He was so short. He was a midget, wasn't he?
那他怎么能当上突击队队员?
Yeah, how did he get to be a Ranger?
他的脚给打断了 所以用手走路
He got shot in the foot once, walking on his hands.
走得很快
He could walk faster on his hands.
跑得更加快
He could run faster on his hands.
维驰奥
Vecchio. Yeah.
卡帕佐
Caparzo.
每当一位弟兄死去
You see, when you end up killing one of your men, -
就要告诉自己  这样能拯救
you tell yourself it happened so you could save the lives of -
二、三、四或十条人命
two, three, or ten others.
甚至是一百人
Maybe 100 others.
你知道我当指挥时 有多少部下阵亡吗?
Do you know how many men I've lost under my command?
多少? 94个
-How many?  -94.
但那代表我救了 十倍那么多的人吗?
But that means I've saved the lives of ten times that many, doesn't it?
甚至是二十倍?
Maybe even 20, right? 20 times as many?
事情就是这么简单
And that's how simple it is.
就是这样把任务与属下之间
That's how you rationalise making the choice -
所做的选择合理化
between the mission and the men.
但这次任务正是救人
Except that this time the mission is a man.
这个瑞恩最好值得我们去救
This Ryan had better be worth it.
他回家后最好能行医救人
He'd better go home and cure some disease -
或发明长寿灯泡什么的
or invent a longer-lasting light-bulb or something.
我想十个瑞恩也抵不了 一个卡帕佐或维驰奥
For the truth is that I wouldn't trade ten Ryans for one Vecchio or Caparzo.
阿们
Amen.
你看  又来了 长官
Look, there it goes again. Sir.
还好吧?
Are you alright?
两小时后出发?小睡片刻吧
We'll move out in two hours. Why don't you get some sleep?
不知道他怎么能做到的 什么?
-I don't know how he does it.  -What's that?
如此熟睡  你看
Falls asleep like that. Look at him.
他躺下就睡着了
The guy's lights-out the minute his head hits the pack.
因为问心无愧 有句话怎么说?
-Clear conscience.  -What's that saying?
神与我们同在 那谁与敌军同在?
God's on our side, who could be on theirs?
若神与我们同在 谁会是我们的对手?
"If God be for us, who could be against us?"
不错  我说了什么?
Yeah, what did I say?
想睡着的话  保持清醒就行了
The trick to falling asleep is trying to stay awake.
为什么  韦德?
How is that, Wade?
我妈当实习医师时 习惯在夜间工作
When my mother was an intern she used to work through the night -
白天睡觉
and sleep through the day.
只有她回家  我们才能聊天
The only time we talked was when she'd get home.
我总会躺着  尽量保持清醒 但从没成功过
I used to lie in bed and stay awake as long as I could,but it never worked
越不想睡  就越快睡着
because the harder I tried the faster I'd fall asleep.
但在家里没关系 因为妈会回家
That wouldn't have mattered in my house.Ma would've come home,
把我弄醒  聊至天亮 聊天时她总是不嫌累
shook me awake,chatted me up 'til dawn.She was never too tired to talk.
也许她在那个时候 才有机会讲话
That's probably the only time she could get a word in.
有趣的是 有时她下班时间早了
Funny thing is,sometimes she would come home early
我会假装睡着
and I'd pretend to be asleep.
谁?你妈? 对
-Who, your mum?  -Yeah.
她会站在门口看着我
She'd stand in the doorway looking at me,
我就闭眼装睡
and I would just keep my eyes shut.
我知道她特地早些回来
And I knew that she just wanted to find out about my day,
跟我聊天  了解那天的生活
that she came home early just to talk to me.
但我却仍然不动 假装已经熟睡
And I still wouldn't move. I'd still pretend to be asleep.
我也不知道为何会那样做
I don't know why I did that.
只有几个钟头  闭嘴睡觉吧
We've only got a couple of hours. Shut up and go to sleep.
上尉?长官?
Captain? Sir?
下士
Corporal.
你怎么了?没事吧?
How are you doing? Are you alright?
还好  我想这一切对我有益
Yeah, I think this is all good for me, sir.
真的?为什么?
Really? How is that?
“战争能训练判断力 磨练意志”
'War educates the senses, calls into action the will," -
“增强体格”
"perfects the physical constitution," -
“人在生死关头的瞬间”
"brings men in such swift and close collision in critical moments," -
“强弱立判”
'that man measures man."
爱默森也许是 这样让自己积极起来的
I guess that's Emerson's way of finding the bright side.
你也有读爱默森? 懂一些
-You know Emerson, sir?   -I know some.
上尉  你来自哪里? 在战前你是做什么的?
So, where are you from, Captain? What did you do before the war?
赌金有多少了?
What's the pool up to?
大概是三百块吧
I think it's around 300, sir.
等到了五百的时候 我就把答案告诉你  瓜分赌金
When it gets up to 500,I'll give you the answer and we'll split the money.
如何?
How about that?
要是你这么想 我就有责任建议你
If that's the way you feel, I feel it's my duty under your command
等赌金累积到一千块
to suggest that we wait until it gets up to 1,000. I think it's...
要是活不了那么久呢?
What if we don't live that long?
五百? 五百好
-500?  -500 would be good, yes.
对  长官
Yes, sir.
睡吧  下士 是  长官
-Get some sleep, Corporal.  -Yes, sir.
谁有磺胺粉?
Who's got sulfa powder?
医护兵  我弟兄在流血 需要止血带
Medic, my buddy's bleeding! He needs a tourniquet.
韦德 什么事?
-Wade.   -Yes, sir?
去帮他一下 是
-See what you can do.   -Yes, sir.
撑着  很快就有人来救你
Hold on, fellas. It won't be much longer.
情况如何?
How are we doing here?
没事的  别担心  医师来了
Alright. You're doing alright, don't worry about it. The Doc's in town.
放心  29步兵团已作突围 很快到这里
Don't worry. The 29th Infantry's breaking through. They'll be here soon.
谁有血浆?
Has anybody got plasma?
上尉
Hey, Captain!
有什么事吗? 我是德温得中尉
-Soldier,you want to fill me in?  -Yeah.Lieutenant DeWindt.
隶属于第99运兵中队 负责运载300与307滑翔机步兵
99th Troop Carrier Squadron carrying in 300th and 307th Glider Infantry.
我是飞行员 二等兵
This one was mine. I was the pilot. Private!
22人阵亡 照顾他
22 men dead. Take care of this one.
我着陆时没受伤 副驾驶却死了
I landed there without a scratch, took my co-pilot's head right off.
这些人是谁?
Who are these people?
我们载的士兵第一晚就离开 之后没再见过他们
The guys we came in with headed off the first night. Haven't seen them since.
期间别的士兵 三五成群地陆续出现
In the meantime other guys keep showing up. One, two, six at a time.
然后有军官来把散兵凑成部队
Then some officer will come along, patch together a mixed unit, -
再次出发作战
and head off to make trouble.
我们在找101师 506B连的二等兵瑞恩
We're looking for a Private Ryan, Baker Company, 506th of the 101st.
这可问倒我了  这里人来人往
You got me. A lot of guys come in and out.
厄本  到那队人里面找瑞恩
Upham! Check out that squad. See if Ryan's in it.
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
莱宾  闻闻他的腿 像不像臭乳酪
Reiben! Smell that leg, right there. Find out if it's south of cheese.
如何?
What?
手放头上
Hands over your head.
别停下来!
Keep moving!
我是犹太人
I'm Jude, you know.
无法把他弄出来  要有绞车
I couldn't pry him out of there. I need a winch.
是的
Yeah.
星级上将 对
-Stars.  -Yeah.
阿门准将 101空降师的副指挥官
Brigadier General Amend. Deputy Commander, 101st.
有些天才提议 在机舱焊接钢板
Some genius had the great idea of welding steel plates onto our deck
以免地面的炮火伤及上将
to keep the General safe from ground fire,
但他们到空降前才告诉我们
but they forgot to tell me until just before we were getting airborne.
就像开货运列车飞行般?
That's like trying to fly a freight train. OK?
负荷过重  地面炮火又猛烈
Gross overload. Trim characteristics all shot to hell.
我为了保持平衡 手几乎都弄断了
I nearly broke both my arms trying to keep her level.
脱勾时我已经尽力了
When we released I cut as hard as I could,
尝试保持高度  以免失速
trying to gain some altitude and keep her from stalling.
最后像陨石一样掉下来 结果变成这样
We came down like a fucking meteor. And this is how we ended up.
其他飞机总算顺利着陆
The others stopped easy enough, though.
我们的飞机太重了
We were just too damn heavy, you know?
草地湿滑  而且是下坡
The grass was wet. Downward slope and all.
死了22人
22 guys dead.
全为了一个上将? 一个人
-All that for a general?  -One man.
这种事很多 “苦差”
There's a lot of that going around. "FUBAR."
“苦差” “苦差”
-"FUBAR."  -"FUBAR."
“苦差” 都说对了
"FUBAR."  -You all got that right.
我在德语字典中 查不到“苦差”
I looked it up in a German dictionary. "FUBAR"'s not there.
厄本  那边也有伞兵
Upham! There are more paratroopers out there.
去找瑞恩
Find out if one of them is Ryan.
你可在这里找找
You might want to check this out, sir.
是兵籍牌  多得数不完
Dog tags. More than I really want to count, sir.
我已盖过许多尸体
I've covered a lot of bodies, sir.
杰克森  从这些开始找吧 是
-Jackson. Start going through those.  -Yes, sir.
我来帮忙
I'll help.
你觉得有那小子吗? 有的话  我会找到的
-Do you think that little prick's in there?  -If he is,I'm going to find him.
我敢说那混蛋... 我打赌他还活着
I bet that son of a bitch... I've got money saying he's still alive.
赌十块我会先找到 来看这里有什么
0 bucks says I nail him first. Let's see what we've got in here.
你没希望了 你认为他在这里面吗?
You mugs don't stand a chance. Do you think he's in here?
继续找吧 好吧
Just keep looking. Alright.
盖瑞艾尼高、班瑞比诺 麦克塞里奥  全都是几内亚人
"Gary lanico", "Ben Rubino", "Mike Cesario"...All the Guineas are buying it.
不是这名字 维维里维基  是你的朋友
Come on, it's not the right name! 'Wee Willie Winkie". A buddy of yours.
我们得找到那混蛋
We've got to find this prick.
那混蛋在哪里?
Where's this son of a bitch?
别混在一起  分开一点
Don't mix them up. Keep them in your pile.
怎么知道哪些是看过的呢?
How am I supposed to know who we've got?
莱宾  闭嘴好吗?
Why don't you just shut up, Reiben?
别吵架 你不高兴吗?
Everybody be friends. Cranky there, huh?
有优胜者了 你说什么?
-I think I've got a winner.  -What are you talking about?
瑞恩 瑞恩?
"Ryan." Ryan?
梅利西  你看 你简直是天才
Take a look at that, Mellis. You're really a genius.
这是里恩  是法语名字 知道这是什么意思吗?
"R-l-E-N-N-E." That's "Rienne" and it's French. Do you know what that means?
一无所获 什么比三条大?
It means "nothing". What beats three of a kind?
这些人全都来自纽约 你老是发牢骚
I got shit here, all guys from New York. You're always bitching.
要帮忙吗? 我葫芦
Do you need a hand? I've got a full house.
我赢了  同花顺
I've got you beat. Straight flush.
你偷看我的牌  你作弊
You're looking at my cards. You're cheating.
笨得太离谱了  你识字吗?
Fucking unreal, this guy. Can you read that shit?
老天  你看这可怜的砘 大概不能防弹吧
Jesus, look at this poor bastard! I guess they're not bulletproof.
应该不能
I guess not.
这砘锩荒源 跟你的那里一样
I don't like what's between his ears.It's like what's between your legs.
对极了 杰克森  说得没错
We've got to give him that. That's not bad for you, Jackson.
我三条 你在干嘛?
I've got three of a kind. What the hell are you doing?
整个空降师都在看着 这可不是扑克牌
The whole goddam Airborne's watching. These aren't poker chips.
好吧 放回去
Alright. Put them back in there.
他不在这里
He's not here.
也许我们该分头去找吧?
Maybe we should split into groups?
到树林里去叫他的名字
Just wander the woods calling his name.
他迟早会听到的  瑞恩
He's bound to hear us sooner or later. Ryan!
上尉  这也不是办法
That might be a little hard to do, Captain.
也许本地人见过他 瑞恩  詹姆斯瑞恩?
Maybe the locals have seen him. Ryan, James Ryan?
瑞恩?有人认识 101空降师的瑞恩吗?
Ryan! Anybody know Ryan, 101st Airborne? You know Ryan?
爱阿华州的二等兵瑞恩?
Private James Ryan from lowa? Anybody know a Ryan?
瑞恩 阿乔
James Ryan! Hey, Joe!
麦可森不是认识C连的瑞恩吗
Doesn't Michaelson pal around with a Ryan from C Company?
应该是 带他过来
I think so. Bring him up.
你认识二等兵瑞恩? 你要大声一点
-You know Private Ryan?  -You have to speak up...
大声一点  我的耳朵不灵光
You have to speak up, sir! My hearing is not so good!
手榴弹在耳朵边爆炸 听力时有时无的
It comes and goes. A grenade went off right by my head.
你认识二等兵瑞恩? 谁?
-Got it. Do you know Private Ryan?   -Who?
二等兵瑞恩?詹姆斯瑞恩? 吉米瑞恩?
-Private Ryan? James Ryan?  -Jimmy Ryan?
詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩
James. James Francis Ryan.
不  是詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩
No, no, no. James Francis Ryan.
给我纸笔
Give me a pencil. Something to write on.
快点  铅笔
Quick, a pencil!
小铅笔给你
Here you are, a small one.
写下来  詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩 爱阿华州?
Write this down: "James Francis Ryan? Iowa?"
你认识他吗?你自己看
"Do you know him?" Read the message! Look!
我当然认识他 知道他在哪里吗?
-Yeah, of course I know him.  -Does he know where he is?
我们偏离了降落区二十英里
Yeah, we missed our dropzone by about 20 miles
降落的地方好像是 布鲁维里什么的
and ended up way over by "Bumville" or some damn place.
我跟他和其他人 正要到了这里集合
Him, me and a couple of others were coming here to the rally point.
却遇到一位上校 正召集弟兄前往兰姆勒
We ran into a colonel who was gathering up men to go to Ramelle.
兰姆勒? 去防守一座桥
Ramelle? To babysit a bridge.
那是我最后一次看见他 好极了  谢谢
-That's the last I've seen of him.  -Great! Thank you!
写谢谢  你看  谢谢 不客气
-Write "Thank you". Read. Thank you.  -You're welcome!
大家过来
Assemble on me.
谢谢你  中尉
Thank you, Lieutenant.
兰姆勒
Ramelle.
我们在这里 兰姆勒在麦德里特河畔
We're here. There. Ramelle is on the Merderet River,right here.
在我们的西南方
Just to the southwest of us.
你知道那座桥吗?
You know anything about that bridge we just talk about?
知道  瑟堡一直是盟军的目标
Yeah. The target has always been Cherbourg.
要占领深水港  才能攻占巴黎 而隆美尔也知道
We can't push on Paris until we take a deep water port and Rommel knows that.
他会试着把装甲部队 运过麦德里特河
He's going to try to get his armour across the Merderet River anyway he can.
这样就能在我们 进攻瑟堡时夹击我们
That way he can hit us in the flank when we make the turn for Cherbourg.
所以有桥梁的村庄 都成了重要的据点
That makes any village on the river with a bridge solid gold real estate.
走吧
Let's go.
上尉
Captain.
那是什么?
What the hell is that?
废弃的雷达站
A radar site. It's got to be out of action.
下面的沙坑里有敌人
Looks like we've got something in that sandbag bunker under the station.
看到吗? 对  我也这么想
-See it?   -Yeah, that's my guess, too.
那是什么? 机枪  或许是MG-42
-What is it?    -Machine gun, probably MG-42.
那些人就是被它干掉的? 也许瑞恩也在里面
-Is that what got those guys?  -Maybe one of them is Ryan.
不  他们是82队的 你的运气才没那么好
No, their patches are 82nd, so your luck's not that good.
我不知道你们的脚程 但若我们悄悄地绕道
I don't know how fast you are, but if we detour this way quick and quiet,
德军就不会知道我们在这里
the Krauts will never even know we were here.
为何不绕道走?
What I'm trying to say is why don't we just go around the thing?
我明白  但不能够这样
I hear what you're saying, but we can't go around it.
我支持莱宾的说法 避开那些机枪就行了
I'm with Reiben. I mean, we left those 88s.
空军可不会专程来 对付一挺机枪
For the Air Force. They're not going to spend ordnance on one machine gun.
上尉
Captain.
绕路还是能达成任务 这并不是我们的任务  对吧?
We can skip it and still accomplish our mission. This isn't our mission, right?
梅利西  你想这样做吗?
Is that what you want to do, Mellish?
任由其他部队中伏?
Leave it here so they can ambush another company?
不  我只是说 这并非我们的目标
No, I'm simply saying it's seems an unnecessary risk given our objective.
我们的目标是打胜仗
Our objective is to win the war.
我有不安的预感
It's just that I don't have a good feeling about this one.
你何时有过好的预感了?
When was the last time you felt good about anything?
好吧  三个人冲前开火
Alright. Three runners with suppressing fire.
梅利西  你跑右边  我跑中间
Mellish. You hook to the right, I'll go up the middle.
谁跑左边?
Who's going left?
我去
I'll do it.
我跑左边 好
-I go left.   -Alright.
厄本  跟杰克森对调 而你待在后面
Upham, switch off with Jackson and you linger in the rear.
我们向前猛攻  迫他换子弹
We advance and keep pressure on him 'til he has to change out his barrels.
然后就扔手榴弹
We should be able to hit them from grenade range.
也许我该跑中间? 你那种跑法?我想不必
-Maybe I should go up the middle?   -The way you run? I don't think so.
也许我该跑左边 也许你该闭嘴
-Maybe I should go left,sir.  -Maybe you should shut up!
莱宾  尽管开火
Reiben, base of fire.
把弹药带在身边
Mags and clips where you can reach them
负责主攻的多带些手榴弹
and extra grenades for the base runners.
山上安全了  干掉了四个 厄本
Hill's clear. Four down and dead! Upham!
收拾装备带上来 我们需要水和药物
Grab the gear and get up here! We need water and extra dressing.
从药包里把吗啡拿出来
Get the morphine out of the medical kit!
混蛋 撒上磺胺粉
Son of a bitch! Get some sulfa on there.
把我的腿抬高 行了
Move my legs up. I got them.
快倒磺胺粉 听我说
Pour sulfa. Listen to my voice.
你会没事的  医师
You're going to be alright, Doc.
没事的  很快就能上医疗船
You're fine. You're going on a hospital ship.
倒多一点 把腿抬起
More sulfa! Move my legs up.
把腿抬高 行了
Put my legs up. I've got them.
你会没事的 没事  医生
You're going to be OK. It's alright, Doc.
厄本  把水壶给我! 快
Upham, give me your canteen! Come on.
我们会带你离开的 压着伤口
We're going to get you out of here. Put some pressure on it.
我中弹了?伤势如何? 替他注射吗啡
Am I shot? How does it look? Give him some morphine.
伤势如何? 你会没事的
How does it look? You're going to be OK.
要注射吗啡了
Here comes the morphine.
被射中脊椎了吗?
Am I shot in the spine?
没事的 是不是射中脊椎?
You're OK. Am I shot in the spine?
抬起他 把他翻过去
Lift him up. Move him over.
压着伤口 轻点
Put some pressure on. Easy, easy.
没事的  医生
It's OK, Doc. It's alright.
韦德  子弹穿了出去 你背后有个弹孔
Wade, you've got an exit wound. It's in the small of your back.
那个洞有多大? 像橡果那么大
-How big is the hole?   -It's about the size of an acorn.
好了 放下他
It's fine. Put him back.
压住伤口
Put some pressure on it. Put some pressure on it.
Put some pressure on it!
用力一点
Put some more pressure on it.
哪里流血较多吗?
Is there anything bleeding worse than the others?
有  这里 知道在哪里吗?这里
Yeah, right here. Do you know what it is? Right here.
我把你的手放到上面 我们正压着伤口
I'll put your hand on it. We got some pressure on there.
就是这里
That's the one.
天啊  那是我的肝脏
Oh, my God! My liver! It's my liver!
教我们该怎么救你
Tell us what to do. Tell us how to fix you.
我们该怎么办?告诉我们
What can we do? Tell us what to do.
给我一点吗啡
I could use a little morphine.
多一点吗啡
More morphine, sir.
好
OK. OK.
如何? 给他吧
-Sir? What?   -Give it to him.
给他吧
Give it to him.
我不想死 韦德  我们正在注射
I don't want to die! Here you go, Wade. Here it comes.
再注射一剂
Give him another one.
妈...
Mama...
Mama.
我想回家...
I want to go home, I want go home.
妈...
Mama, Mama, Mama...
Mama, Mama, Mama, Mama...
莱宾  抓住他
Reiben, hold him!
等一下
Not yet!
先叫他替韦德掘坟
First make him mark and cover Wade's body for Grave Detail.
也替那些伞兵掘坟
Same thing for the paratroopers down there.
拿走他的装备  查问他
Strip that stuff off him. Check him for intelligence.
问这混蛋  韦德是不是他杀的 快问
Ask this piece of shit if he shot Wade! Ask him!
有用吗? 有
-Does it matter?   -It does!
闭上你的脏嘴
Shut up with that filthy pig Latin.
杰克森  你中弹了吗?
Jackson, are you hit?
只是擦伤罢了
It just skinned the arm.
把伤口处理好 你跟中士留意周围
Get it cleaned and dressed. You and Sarge watch the perimeter.
他求我们别杀他 厄本  我不管他说什么
He says, "Please don't shoot." I don't care what he says, Upham.
长官?你要让他们杀他?
Sir? Sir, are you going to let them kill him?
这是不对的 那你去帮他埋尸体
This is not right, sir. You can help him with the bodies.
怎么了?
What is happening?
美国人
American.
我喜欢美国人
I like American.
轮船威里
Steamboat Willie.
轮船威里 轮船威里  美国人
Steamboat Willie. Steamboat Willie. American.
他说他还没完成 那是你的想法  来吧
He says he's not finished. That's what you think. Come on.
求求你  我喜欢美国人
Please! I like America!
美国什么都好
Fancy schmancy! What a cinch!
美国什么都有
Go fly a kite! Cat got your tongue! Cool beans!
贝蒂小姐  好性感
Betty Boop! What a dish.
贝蒂嘉宝  腿很美
Betty Grable. Nice gams.
我说你看到吗?
I say can you see
我说...
I say...
去你的希特勒
Fuck Hitler.
Fuck Hitler!
长官  他说他替韦德难过...
Sir, he says he's sorry about Wade. He says he's sorry about Wade.
上尉
Captain!
上尉  你也知道这样做不对的
Captain, this isn't right. You know this.
他是战俘  他已经投降了
He's a prisoner. He surrendered. He surrendered, sir!
叫他...
Tell him...
朝那方向走一千步 然后脱掉蒙眼布
to march 1,000 paces in that direction.Then he can take off the blindfold.
向盟军自首
He turns himself in to the first Allied patrol.
你在说笑吗?放他走?
Are you kidding? We're letting him go?
莱宾  他是战俘 不能带着他走
He's a POW, Reiben. We can't take him with us.
我军自会处置他 算他命大
Our guys will pick him up. That was a close shave.
真幸运
Lucky Strikes.
带我去看球赛
Take me out to the ball game...
万一他被敌军救回 又会回来作战的
Only if he doesn't get picked up by his own and get thrown back into circulation.
上尉  你白白放过了敌人 简直白痴
Captain, you just let the enemy go. This is such bullshit.
没错 白痴?这是白痴?
You all got that right. Bullshit? This is bullshit?
难道可以射杀战俘? 这样是有违军法的
Shooting a prisoner is OK? It's against the rules!
军法跟你的新朋友一起走了
The goddam rules just walked off with your new friend.
上尉  这样做是对的吧?
But I guess that was the decent thing to do, Captain?
收拾东西  出发吧
Get your gear. Let's go.
你们听到了  收拾东西
You heard him. Gear up.
上尉刚下了命令 对
The Captain just gave you an order. Yeah.
就像他下令攻下机枪台一样 真是大英雄
Like the one he gave to take this machine gun. That was a real doozy.
你太过分了
You're out of line!
他命令我们拿下这里真是英明
That was one hell of a call coming to take this nest,
但我们却因此丧失了一位队友
but what the hell, we only lost one of our guys going for it.
瑞恩妈妈一定很高兴 知道她的小宝贝的性命
I hope Mama Ryan's really happy knowing that little Jimmy's life
比我们两位队友的还重要
was more important than two of our guys!
但我们还没找到他吧?
But then, we haven't found them, have we?
你... 别碰我
Hey... Get off me!
莱宾  起来
Reiben, get up.
拿起东西  入列
Gear up. Fall in.
我要退出这项任务
I'm done with this mission.
等等
Hey! Hey!
长官... 你不能背弃上尉
Sir... Don't you walk away from your captain!
莱宾  给我回来 不
-Reiben, get back in line!   -No, sir.
我宁可坐牢也不想继续了
I'll spend the rest of my life in the stockade rather than go on.
我不会再问你的了 上尉
I'm not going to ask you again. Captain!
白痴 入列
This is bullshit! Fall in!
你要因为瑞恩而杀我? 不  是因为我讨厌你
-Are you going to shoot me over Ryan?   -No, because I don't like you.
他想走  就让他走吧
If he wants to go, just let him go!
你不管吗? 上尉  你看到了吗?
Are you letting this happen? Captain! You see this?
上尉  瑞恩已经死了
Captain. Sir, Ryan's dead.
白痴 这里情况不妙
Bullshit! We have a situation here.
我有很强的第六感
I have a sixth sense. I know it in my bones.
你不杀德军却要杀我?
We didn't kill the Kraut. Now you're going to shoot me.
他比你好 下手吧
-He's better than you.  -Just do it!
打我的腿... 我要打你的大嘴巴
-Put one in my leg...  -I'll shoot you in your big mouth!
废话少说  开枪吧
Put your money where your mouth is and do it!
你总是那么多说话
You don't know how to shut up.
上尉  求求你 赌金有多少了?
-Captain, please!  -What's the pool on me up to?
你是个懦弱的混蛋 中士  我在等你开枪
-You are a coward son of a bitch!  -I'm waiting, Sarge.
赌金累积到有多少了?
What's the pool on me up to right now?
有多少了?
What's it up to?
三百块吗?
What is it? 300 dollars, is that it?
我是个老师
I'm a schoolteacher.
我教英文作文
I teach English Composition...
在宾夕法尼亚州一个叫 艾德里的小镇
in this little town called Addley, Pennsylvania.
这十一年来我在 汤玛斯爱迪生高校任教
In the last 11 years, I've been at Thomas Alva Edison High School.
在春季我是棒球教练
I was the coach of the baseball team in the springtime.
我真该死
I'll be doggone.
我在家乡告诉人家我的职业时
Back home, when I tell people what I do for a living
他们觉得“一看就知道”
they think, 'Well, that figures."
但到了这里
But over here, it's...
却成为了一个大秘密
a big, big mystery.
我想我变了一点
So, I guess I've changed some.
有时我想我改变了很多
Sometimes I wonder if I've changed so much
回家后也许妻子会不认得我
my wife is even going to recognise me whenever I get back to her...
或许我不能向她...
and how I'll ever be able to...
诉说像今天这种事情
tell her about days like today.
瑞恩
Ryan...
我对瑞恩一无所知  我才不管
I don't know anything about Ryan. I don't care.
他跟我毫无关系 那只是个名字
He means nothing to me, it's just a name,
但要是到兰姆勒带他回家
but if going to Ramelle and finding him so he can go home,
能让我回到妻子身边
if that earns me the right to get back to my wife, then...
我会接下这项任务
...then that's my mission.
你想退出?你想去作战?
You want to leave? You want to go off and fight the war?
没关系
Alright.
我不会阻止你 我甚至会替你申请
Alright, I won't stop you. I'll even put in the paperwork.
我只知道每多杀一个人 我就离开我的家越远
I just know that with every man I kill, the farther away from home I feel.
昔日的回忆涌现
by memories of days gone by
孤独中你嘲弄我
In my solitude you taunt me
勾起不死的记忆
with memories that never die
我坐在椅上  满怀绝望
I sit in my chair filled with despair
比任何人都要哀伤
There's no one could be so sad
看着坐着的地方 尽是阴霾
With gloom everywhere I sit and I stare
我很快就会疯掉
I know that I'll soon go mad
有坦克  躲好
Half-track! Cover!
是谁开枪?
Who's doing the shooting? Who's doing the shooting?
准备行动  攻击左边
Get ready to move. Take their left flank!
慢着  提防有诈
Hold on and make sure they're down.
我们是101师  要出来了
101st! We're coming out!
装甲兵第二师
That was a recon. element, 2nd SS.
我们正在等待情报 一定是他们了
We've been expecting a probe. That must have been it.
第二突击队C连米勒上尉
Captain Miller, Charlie Company, 2nd Rangers.
501师E连汉德森下士
Corporal Henderson, Easy Company, 501st.
506团第一队瑞恩 506团第三队托恩比
Ryan, First of 506th. Toynbee, Third of 506th.
詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩? 对  你怎么会知道?
-James Francis Ryan?  -Yes,sir.How did you guess that?
看来敌方攻势猛烈 对  是小组部队的进攻
-Looks like you got hit pretty hard.  -Yes,sir.Small unit action.
他们的88公厘炮威力强劲
They came in and beat the hell out of us with 88s.
要是你们就是救兵 我可要投诉
Tell you what. If you're our relief, I'm going to file a complaint.
我不会怪你
I wouldn't blame you.
谁是你的指挥官?
Who's your CO?
原本是简宁斯上尉
It would've been Captain Jennings.
但现在唯有以下士充当指挥
I'm afraid the best we can muster up now is a corporal.
那你们为何来这里?
So what are you guys all about?
我们为他而来  瑞恩
We're here for him. Ryan.
我?
Me, sir?
你是爱阿华州的 詹姆斯法兰西斯瑞恩吧?
James Francis Ryan of lowa?
对  爱阿华州佩顿市 这是怎么回事?
Yes, sir. Peyton,Iowa, that's correct. What is this about?
你兄长阵亡了
Your brothers were killed in combat.
哪个?
Which ones?
全部
All of them.
真的?
On the level?
恐怕是真的
Yeah, I'm afraid so.
大概要一段时间才能接受
You might want to take some time with this.
要是你想到什么地方...
If there's someplace you want to go and...
是怎么回事? 瑞恩的兄弟去世了
-What's this all about?  -Ryan lost his brothers.
哪个? 全部
-Which one?  -All of them.
你们专程跑来告诉我?
You came all the way out here to tell me that?
你要回家
You're going home.
我们奉命带你回去
Our orders are to bring you back.
带我回去?
Bring me back?
下士  我并非想落井下石 但军令如山
Corporal,I don't mean to leave you more short-handed,but orders are orders.
想跟什么人联络吗?
Any communications about when you will be relieved?
我们也不知道南方的情况
We can't tell. We don't know what's happening south of us.
但我的命令不许我擅离职守
My orders don't include me abandoning my post.
一切以这道命令作准
I understand that, but this changes things.
我不认同
I don't see that it does, sir.
这是美军参谋长的命令
The Chief of Staff for the US Army says it does.
我们奉命死守这座桥
Our orders are to hold this bridge at all costs.
我方战机已经把麦德里特河的 所有桥梁炸断
Our planes in the 82nd have taken out every bridge across the Merderet,
除了瓦隆尼和这里两处
with the exception of two: one at Valognes and this one.
要是给德军拿下 我们就要退守
If the Germans take it, we'll have to displace.
部队的任务是一回事 但你要离开了
Private.It's one thing that your outfit wants to stay,but your party's over here.
援军到达前我不能离开
I can't leave before the reinforcements are here.
三分钟内收拾行装
You've got three minutes to get your gear.
那他们怎么办 混蛋
-What about them,there's barely...  -Hey,asshole!
我们两位队友已经为你送命
Two of our guys already died trying to find you.
真的? 不错
-Sir?  -That's right.
他们叫什么名字? 艾文韦德和艾德林卡帕佐
-What were their names?  -Irwin Wade and Adrian Caparzo.
韦德和谁?
Wade and?
卡帕佐
Caparzo.
没有理由要这样
It doesn't make any sense.
这样没道理 我何德何能  可以先走?
It doesn't make any sense, sir. Why do I deserve to go?
为何不是他们? 他们也同样努力
Why not any of these guys? They all fought just as hard as me.
你死后传讯员就要跟...
Is that what they're supposed to tell your mother
你母亲这样说?
when they send her another folded American flag?
跟她说你在这里找到我
Tell her that when you found me I was here,
我要跟军中其他手足一起
and I was with the only brothers that I have left,
我怎样也不会离弃他们
and that there was no way I was going to desert them.
她应该会明白 我不会离开这座桥
I think she'll understand that. There's no way I'm leaving this bridge.
现在怎么办?
What are your orders?
中士  我们进入了 一个奇异的国度
Sergeant, we have crossed some strange boundary here.
一切都异乎寻常
Our world has taken a turn for the surreal.
但问题始终要解决
Clearly, but the question still stands.
我不知道  你觉得怎样?
I don't know. What do you think?
你不会想知道
You don't want to know what I think.
不  我想知道
No, Mike, I do.
我其中一个想法是 如他所言  他何德何能?
Part of me thinks the kid's right. What's he done to deserve this?
他既然想留下来 我们就干脆回去
If he wants to stay here, fine. Let's leave him and go home.
不错
Yeah.
但我还有一个想法 要是我们也留下来
But another part of me thinks, "What if by some miracle we stay
会缔造什么奇迹呢?
and actually make it out of here?"
有天我们回想此事
Some day we might look back on this and decide that
也许会觉得在这场混帐战争中
saving Private Ryan was the one decent thing we pulled out of
拯救瑞恩是唯一的好事
this whole godawful, shitty mess.
这是我的想法 上尉  如你所言
That's what I was thinking, sir. Like you said, Captain.
我们会留下来 一起为团聚战斗
We do that, we all earn the right to go home.
兄弟
Oh, brother...
就只有这些
This is everything.
0.230机枪、17枚手榴弹 11个霍金斯地雷
You've got the.230 calibre machine guns, 17 grenades, 11 Hawkins mines.
你有两支火箭筒 但只能发射八次
You've got two bazookas, but they've only got eight rounds left.
还有各式小手枪
And assorted small arms.
本来有0.60迫击炮  但已损毁
We had a.60 mortar, but an arty round took it out.
敌军坦克压过来 吐口水攻击好了
Might as well be spit wads if they roll on us with tanks.
敌军当然会动用坦克 你意下如何?
Which they're sure to do. What are you thinking, sir?
我提议进行夹击
I'm thinking I'm going to whip around the flanks.
要把他们引到大街
Unless we can draw them up the main road between the buildings,
用瓦砾造一个瓶颈
where all the rubble makes a bit of a bottleneck
让坦克无用武之地? 可以的话
-Disable him?   -If we can.
造个六十吨的路障 然后展开夹击
Make a 60-tonne roadblock. Then we've got a fighting chance at her flanks.
好  分散他们  别让他们集结
Good. Split them up, don't let them mass.
然后逐一击破  再退回大桥
Hit them hard one-on-one, and fall back to the bridge.
下面放一台机枪 另一台置于高处
Machine gun on the move down here, number two up high to piss on them.
计划就是这样  杰克森
That would be the idea. Jackson!
可以的话  我想你去钟楼
If we can, I'd like to get you up in that bell tower.
知道 我会给你安排帮手
Yes, sir. I'll give you some company.
也好  还要0.30狙击枪 和一千发子弹
Some company couldn't hurt. A.30 with about a 1,000 rounds would be OK.
帕克  有份优差
Parker, job opportunity.
这主意不错
It's not the worst idea ever,
但胜负关键在于 把坦克弄到街上让我们夹击
but everything depends on getting the tank down the road for us to knock out.
你有什么主意?
How the hell do you plan on doing that?
他说得对  空降师的队友刚说
He's right. As our colleague from Airborne pointed out
我们有的是口水
what we've got is a bunch of spit wads.
但把坦克引来后  如何应付?
How do we stop the tank if we get it to commit?
先用兔子引它追赶
Give it a rabbit to chase.
接着攻击坦克的履带
We could hit the tank in the tracks.
对  但用什么攻击?
Yeah, but with what?
用粘附式炸弹 粘附式炸弹?
-We could try a sticky bomb.  -Sticky bomb, sir?
你编出来的吧?
Sir, are you making that up?
不  你可以去翻翻作战手册
No, it's in the field manual. Check it out, if you want to.
手册不知道在那里 你尽管讲解一下
We seem to be out of field manuals. Perhaps you could enlighten us.
有炸药吧?黄色炸药 还是B成分炸药?
You have some demolition, don't you? TNT or Composition B?
很多  桥那里的B炸药 足以把桥炸断两次
Plenty. I've got that bridge wired with enough Composition B to blow it twice.
那拿一点出来
You can spare some, then.
塞满军装袜子
You take a standard GI sock, cram it full with Composition B,
再加进导火线  表面涂满机油
and rig up a simple fuse. Then you coat the whole thing with axle grease.
炸弹扔出  就能粘附于目标物
That way, when you throw it, it should stick.
有粘力  所以叫粘附式炸弹
It's a bomb that sticks. It's a sticky bomb.
有更好的方法  尽管说出来
Come up with a better way to knock the tracks off a tank, I'm all ears.
这主意不错  大家要缴袜了
This is good. Now we have to surrender our socks!
拉上去
Haul away.
选择攻击范围 与钟楼组成交叉火力网
Select the field of fire. Crossfire with the one in the bell tower.
我负责12到9
I can cover 12 to 9 from here.
慢慢来 行了
Easy! I've got her!
这是地雷
Here are the mines.
要配置得当才行
For being the best we can do,
前头的机枪位置不太好
that forward machine gun is not in a terrible firing position.
应该放到这里
And this position right here...
这是最后防线
This is the Alamo.
要是退到这里 最后一个活人负责炸桥
They push us this far, the last man alive blows the bridge.
导火线能烧三十秒  告诉大家
We've only got a 30-second delay on the fuse, so tell everyone
点火后快逃  不然性命不保
that if you're last you'd better hurry or you'll not live long.
上尉?我有什么任务?
Captain? Where am I during all this?
留在我两英尺之内  不许有异议
Never more than two feet away from me. And that's not negotiable.
跟我去拿弹药
I'm going to get some ammo. Come on.
厄本  听着 是的
Hey, Upham, listen to me. Yes.
你在听吗? 是的
-Are you listening?  -Yes.
我们会不断东奔西跑
We're going to be displacing and falling back like crazy sons of bitches,
你要运送弹药  随传随到 不然我们就死定
so you've got to be Johnny-on-the-spot with the ammo,or we're dead.
你明白吗? 随传随到
-Do you understand?  -Johnny-on-the-spot.
你没事吧? 没事
-Yeah. Are you alright?  -Yeah.
我们从英国出发时 也会分发香烟
When we shipped out of England we got cigarettes
我却说“谢谢  我不抽烟”
and I said, "No, thank you. I don't smoke."
形势很凶险吧? 难以置信
-Quite a situation, huh?  -Unbelievable.
这差事混帐得不得了
Yeah. "Fucked-Up Beyond All Recognition", right?
不错
You've got that right.
“苦差” 对
-"FUBAR"!   -Alright!
很痛
Ouch.
这可不是玩的
Yeah, well... It's going to be a real show, huh?
知道了
Yeah, OK.
放轻松
Take it easy.
“苦差”
"FUBAR."
是谁的歌声?
Who's that singing, sir?
艾迪斯皮雅福
Edith Piaf.
她为何这么伤心?
What is she so upset about?
情人离异 但他的面容历历在目
Her lover left her, but she still sees his face everywhere she goes.
就是这样
That would do it.
生命中就只有你
"Even life itself only represents you."
梦着你拥我入怀
"Sometimes I dream that I'm in your arms."
什么?她曾经唱过 是副歌
What was that? She sang it before. The chorus.
副歌
The chorus.
每当你耳语喃喃
"And you speak softly in my ear."
都让我闭目静听
"And you say things that make my eyes close."
感觉美妙
"And I find that marvellous."
厄本
Again, Upham...
老实说  你使我兴奋莫名
...to be honest, I find myself curiously aroused by you.
棒极了
Marvellous.
这首歌很哀伤  开始时她唱着
It's a really melancholy song. At the beginning of the song she says:
你离去后  我就伤心绝望
"And then one day you left me and I've been desperate ever since."
漫天满地  都是你的影子
"I see you all over the sky, I see you all over the earth."
再听多几首这种歌 不用德军开枪
Any more songs like this, the Krauts won't have to shoot me.
我就割脉自杀了
I'm just going to slit my own wrists.
厄本  你好奇怪
You're a strange bird, Upham.
对不起  是艾迪斯
I'm sorry. It's Edith, you know.
可知道这首歌让我想起什么?
You know what that song reminds me of?
瑞雪太太在我出发前的一番话
Mrs. Rachel Troubowitz and what she said when I left for Basic.
她说“别碰我”?
What? "Don't touch me?"
不  她是公寓管理员的妻子
No. She's our Super's wife.
她到我妈的店买衣服 胸围有44EE
She comes into my mum's shop to try a few things. She's like a 44 Double E.
不得了
Double E? They're massive.
好大的奶奶
Those are big titties.
我骗她穿42D的衣服 我们在更衣室里
I've got her convinced that she's a 42 D. So we're in the dressing room
她尝试挤进那件丝带束腰
and she tries to get into this side-cut,silk-ribboned,triple-panel girdle
还有神奇胸罩
with the shelf-lift brassiere.
很好看  都挤了出来
It's beautiful. She's pouring out of this thing.
很紧吗? 不  很好看
-Is it tight?  -No, it's beautiful.
她看得出我的小弟 像自由神像般又大又硬
She sees me and can tell I've got a hard-on the size of the Statue of Liberty.
于是她叫我冷静
She says, "Richard, calm down", and she says,
又说要是在战场上难过害怕
"Over there, if you see anything that upsets you, if you're scared,"
就闭眼想想它们
"I want you to close your eyes and think of these, you understand?"
我说我明白了
So I said, "Yes, ma'am."
你没事吧?
Are you alright, sir?
我在数拍子
Yeah, I'm just keeping the rhythm.
你在老家真的是老师?
Is it true you were a teacher back home?
对 我是当不上老师的了
-Yes.   -That's something I could never do.
我家兄弟都不听老师的话
Not with the way me and my brothers treated our teachers. No, sir!
我教过上千个你这样的孩子
I had a thousand kids like you.
我想不起哥哥的容貌
I can't see my brothers' faces.
怎样努力也想不起来 你试过这样吗?
I've been trying and I can't see their faces at all. Has that happened to you?
你要想想发生过的事
You've got to think of a context.
那是什么意思?
What does that mean?
不能只想他们的样子 要想些具体事情
You don't just think about their faces, you think about something specific,
你们的共同经历
something you've done together.
我想家的时候  想得很具体
When I want to think of home, I think of something specific.
我想起后院的吊床
I think of my hammock in the backyard, -
或者是妻子戴起我的旧手套 修剪玫瑰花丛
or my wife pruning the rose bushes in a pair of my old work gloves.
有一晚两个哥哥把我弄醒
This one night, two of my brothers woke me up in the middle of the night.
说要给我惊喜
They said they had a surprise for me.
他们带我到谷仓阁楼
They took me to the barn up into the loft
原来大哥丹尼...
and there was my oldest brother Dan
跟爱莉丝贾汀在里面
with Alice Jardine!
想像一下  那女孩从一株 丑陋的树上掉下来
Picture a girl who just took a nosedive from the ugly tree
会让所有树枝都给压断
and hit every branch coming down!
丹尼脱去她的衬衫
And Dan's got her shirt off...
接着要把胸罩也脱下时 肖恩突然大叫
So he's trying to get her bra off and all of a sudden Sean screams out
“丹尼  你年纪还小 不可以这样”
"Danny, you're a young man. Don't do it!"
爱莉丝贾汀马上大叫 跳了起来
Alice Jardine hears this and she screams and jumps up
想冲出去 但她的头给衬衫蒙着
and tries to run out, but she's got her shirt over her head.
所以撞到墙壁  晕倒了
She runs into the wall and knocks herself out.
丹尼很生气  追着我们
Now Dan is so mad at us. He starts coming after us,
但爱莉丝晕倒了  他要弄醒她
but at the same time Alice is unconscious. He's got to wake her up.
于是一手抓着她的腿猛拉
He grabs her by a leg and drags her
一手拿着铲子追赶肖恩
and at the same time he picks up a shovel and goes after Sean!
肖恩说“你干嘛打我? 我是在帮你”
And Sean says, 'Why are you trying to hit me? I just did you a favour!"
丹尼更加生气  乱挥铲子
This makes Dan more angry. He tries to swing this thing.
最后铲子脱手  打破了火油灯
He loses his shovel. It goes out of his grasp and hits a kerosene lantern.
爆炸着火  谷仓几乎给烧掉
The thing explodes. The whole barn almost goes up because of this thing.
这就是最后一晚 丹第二天就上战场去
That was it, that was the last... Dan went off to Basic the next day.
这是四兄弟最后一次共聚
That was the last night the four of us were together.
已经过了两年
That was two years ago.
天啊
Oh, my.
再说说妻子和玫瑰花丛的事
Tell me about your wife and those rose bushes.
不  那些事要留给自己
No. No, that one I save just for me.
敌人从东面开来
Enemy from the east.
两台虎式坦克  两辆装甲车
He sees two Tiger tanks, two Panzer tanks.
五十人以上的步兵队伍
Infantry. 50 plus change.
分散  各就各位 莱宾  去当兔子
Disperse! You know what to do. Reiben, get on the rabbit.
厄本  躲起来 梅利西、汉德森  准备开火
Upham, get some cover. Mellish and Henderson, lock and load!
大家检查武器
Everybody check your ammo!
莱宾  祝你好运 不用祝福  我生来幸运
-Good luck,Reiben!  -I don't need any luck,I was born lucky!
拿着五枚曳光弹 知道  照亮两端
One in five tracer. Yes, and tracers point both ways.
去检查顶端的空间
Why don't you check the head space and she should run.
厄本  快点
Upham, hustle up!
厄本下士  这里没有0.30机枪
Corporal Upham. We don't have a.30 calibre machine gun here.
梅利西和钟楼的 杰克森才需要这个
Either Mister Mellish or Mr Jackson in the bell tower needs that.
厄本  杰克森有子弹 去拿给梅利西
Upham! Jackson's fine, turn around to Mellish!
有很多步兵  不知道会否上钓
There's a ton of infantry. I don't know if they took the bait, though.
还有口香糖吗?
Have you got any more of that?
装甲车没有上当
The Panzers didn't take the bait.
步兵团正向左进发
The infantry's moving to the left.
一辆装甲车跟二十人刚刚开过
A half-track just went by with about 20 troops.
梅利西、汉德森  移位
Mellish, Henderson! Displace!
点火
Do it, now! Light it up! You! Light it!
右边有三十人  设法截停他们
30 infantry on the right flank. Get over there, find a hole and stop them!
移位
Displace!
厄本
Upham!
目标清除 去吧
Clear! OK, go!
德国人
Krauts!
向右边进攻
Right flank!
伏下
Get down, get down!
厄本  0.30子弹
Upham! Thirty cal, hurry!
告诉上尉  左翼快失守
Find the Captain, this flank's going to fold!
车子还在动
Traversing! He's still in this fight!
瑞恩  伏下
No! Ryan, get down, get down!
瑞恩
Ryan!
闭嘴 放开我
Keep your mouth shut Get off me!
你没事吧? 放开我
-Are you alright?  -Get off of me!
上尉  我也没事  谢谢
I'm fine too, Captain. Thanks.
夹击他们  扔手榴弹过去
Hit them from both sides. Get aboard! Get a grenade in there!
手榴弹
Grenade!
是二十毫米机枪
20 mill! 20 mill!
是重型机枪  干掉它
Flak gun, 20 mm. Take it out!
机枪给覆盖着  打不到
Heavy weapon in defilade below! I ain't got a shot!
钳子队形  帕克 目标在八点钟方向
Pincer move! Parker! Targets eight o'clock, low!
愿天主赐我力量
God grant me strength.
去吧  移位
Let's go, displace! Come on!
厄本  躲好
Cover! Upham, cover!
0.30子弹用光了
I'm out of.30 calibre.
天主赐我力量  教我的手打仗
Blessed be the Lord my strength, which teaches my hands to war -
教我的指头作战
and my fingers to fight.
天主是我的堡垒 我的高塔和解脱者
My goodness and my fortress. My high tower and deliverer.
我的盾牌  我的依靠
My shield and He in whom I trust.
去吧  宝贝
Here you go, baby.
帕克  伏下
Parker, get down!
上尉  那机枪很要命
Captain, that 20 mm is killing us.
一定要毁掉它 我到上面去
-We've got to try to flank it somehow.  -Let me get over there for a top shot.
厄本
Upham!
厄本  拿子弹来
Upham, Upham! Upham, ammo, goddammit!
卡住了  拿0.30子弹给我 用光了
-I'm jammed! Got any.30 calibre?   -I'm out.
厄本
Upham. Upham!
莱宾
Reiben!
用光了  有人有子弹吗?
I'm out! I need another bandolier. Anybody got a bandolier?
混蛋
You piece of shit!
住手  听我说  别这样
Let's stop, let's stop! Listen to me! Stop! No, no, no...
去你的
Fuck!
混蛋...
Son of a bitch, son of a bitch!
混蛋
Son of a bitch!
用光了 那些0.60炮弹...
I'm out! Those.60 rounds...
没有炮管也可以用 怎样用?
-We can use them without the tube.   -How?
这是引爆线  扔出去就行了
Fuse-arming wire, set back and heave it!
德国人
Panzer schreck!
去吧
Go, go!
到最后防线去
We're going to the Alamo.
最后防线
Alamo! Alamo!
交给我们  你们撤退 你跟着来
We'll take it. You fall back! You be right behind us!
我们很快回来
As soon as we're in business.
莱宾  移位
Displace. Reiben!
装弹
Reload!
开炮
Alright, go!
要炸桥了  快逃 快离开
We're blowing the bridge! Get off! Off the bridge!
中士  麦克  你没事吧?
Sarge! Mike, are you alright?
被风吹倒了 走吧
-I just got the wind knocked out of me.  -Let's go!
躲好  要炸桥了
Take cover, we're going to blow this bridge!
来吧
Come on!
虎式坦克要过桥了
Tiger company's coming across the bridge.
上尉  找个地方躲好
Captain, get behind something!
麦克
Mike!
上尉  你去哪里?回来
Captain, where the hell are you going? Captain, get back here!
厄本
Upham!
撑着
Hang in there.
救护员
Medic!
有救护员吗?
Medic! We've got a medic?
是P-51反坦克轰炸机
They're tankbusters, sir. P-51s.
我们的守护天使
Angels on our shoulders.
什么事?
What, sir?
詹姆斯
James...
别辜负
Earn this.
别辜负大家
Earn it.
“亲爱的瑞恩太太”
"My dear Mrs Ryan."
“我有个喜讯要带给你”
"It's with a profound sense of joy that I write to inform you"
“就是令O二等兵 詹姆斯瑞恩安然无恙”
"that your son, Private James Ryan, is well"-
“现在正从欧洲的战线回国”
"and at this moment on his way home from European battlefields."
“詹姆斯尽忠职守”
"Reports indicate that James did his duty in combat"
“勇气过人  坚毅不屈”
"with great courage and steadfast dedication"
“纵使他得悉兄弟阵亡”
"even after he was informed of the loss your family has suffered"
“仍坚持参与这场 铲除独裁暴政的伟大抗争”
"in this great campaign to rid the world of tyranny and oppression."
“我与战争部长”
"I take great pleasure injoining the Secretary of War, "
“美军同仁及美国国民”
"the men and women of the US Army, and the citizens of a grateful nation"
“仅此祝你身体健康 与詹姆斯一起活得愉快”
"in wishing you good health and many years of happiness with James."
“虽然爱子平安归国”
"Nothing, not even the safe return of a beloved son"
“也无法弥补你 和千千万万个美国家庭”
"can compensate you or the thousands of other American families"
“在战争中遭受的创痛”
"who have suffered great loss in this tragic war."
“我想与你分享”
"I might share with you some words"-
“一番在悲痛绝望中 支持着我的说话”
"which have sustained me through nights of peril, loss and heartache, "
“是这样的一番说话”
"and I quote, 'I pray that our heavenly Father"
“愿天主安抚你的丧子之痛”
"may assuage the anguish of your bereavement"
“让你永远怀念远去的挚爱”
"and leave you only the cherished memory of the loved and lost"
“神圣的荣耀都归于你们”
"and the solemn pride that must be yours"
“因你们为自由 付出了重大的代价”
"to have laid a so costly a sacrifice upon the altar of freedom."
“林肯敬上”
"Abraham Lincoln."
“深表敬意”
"Yours very sincerely and respectfully,"
“参谋长马歇尔上将”
"George C. Marshall. General, Chief of Staff."
今天我家人也来了 他们想跟我来
My family is with me today. They wanted to come with me.
说真的  我不知道到这里来 会有什么感受
To be honest with you, I wasn't sure how I would feel coming back here.
我每天都想着 当日你在桥上说的话
Every day, I think about what you said to me that day on the bridge.
我尽力活好我的人生
I've tried to live my life the best I could.
希望这已经足够
I hope that was enough.
希望这至少让你觉得...
I hope that at least in your eyes...
我没有辜负 你们为我做的一切
l've earned what all of you have done for me.
詹姆斯
James.
“约翰米勒上尉”
"Captain John H. Miller."
跟我说我这辈子没白活 什么?
-Tell me I have led a good life. -What?
跟我说  我是好人
Tell me I'm a good mess.
你是好人
You are.
（米勒上尉，宾州第二突击队　卒于1944年6月13日）